Finding Aid for Temple Beth Emeth (Ann Arbor, Mich.) Records, 1966-2009
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Temple Beth Emeth (Ann Arbor, Mich.) records 1966-2009, 1966-1995
Temple Beth Emeth (Ann Arbor, Mich.)
10 linear feet
00131 Ba 2
Reform Jewish temple located in Ann Arbor, Michigan. Temple Beth Emeth shares facilities with St. Clare's Episcopal Church. Minutes of board and congregational meetings; publications include history of the temple and service bulletins; subject files relate to community involvement and issues; and visual materials.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The records were deposited by Temple Beth Emeth (Donor no. 6743 ) in August 2000. Additional records were received in 2005 and 2011.
The record group is open to research.
For many years, Beth Israel Synagogue, founded in 1916, was the only Jewish congregation in the Ann Arbor-Ypsilanti area. As such, it tried to fulfill the religious needs of all members. In 1966, Professor Ronald Tikofsky initiated a meeting in the hopes of establishing a Reform Jewish temple. Beginning with a small gathering in his home, in February 1966, and with help from the regional director of the Union of American Hebrew Congregations (UAHC), a preliminary steering committee was formed. Several community meetings were held. With Ron Tikofsky as president, the group began to formulate plans for religious worship and a religious education program. Beth Emeth, House of Truth, was chosen as the name for the new temple in the Ann Arbor community.
Temple Beth Emeth held its first services Friday August 19, 1966 at the Congregational Church on State and William Street, with Dr. Richard Hertz of Temple Beth El in Detroit as guest Rabbi. A Torah and prayer books were donated by members of that congregation.
With the opening of the Religious School in September, the Temple moved to the First Unitarian Church at 1917 Washtenaw Avenue. Services were held on a bi-weekly basis, and religious school convened on Saturday mornings. In the early years, services were conducted by Temple members or by guest rabbis in the region. Sermons were often delivered by community leaders or by the members themselves. For the first two years, Dr. Robert Katz, Professor at Hebrew Union College, Cincinnati, officiated at High Holy Day observances.
In 1968, Bruce S. Warshal was engaged as a senior rabbinical student to serve the Temple on a bi-weekly basis. The following year, after his ordination from Hebrew Union College in Cincinnati, Rabbi Warshal agreed to serve as the first full time Rabbi of Temple Beth Emeth.
As the congregation grew from approximately thirty families in 1968 to almost 100 families over the next two years, it became necessary to relocate the religious school to larger accommodations. In the summer of 1970, an agreement was negotiated with the Ann Arbor Public Schools to rent Lawton Elementary School on Sunday mornings. The congregation was already holding weekly Friday evening services, alternating one week at the Unitarian Church and one week in the homes of members. By January, the Temple Board appropriated the extra funds required to rent the church for weekly Sabbath worship. Around this time the congregation began to realize other needs as well. A long range planning committee was formed to consider all options. In 1971, after extensive searching and much debate, the congregation leased the sanctuary of St. Clare's Episcopal Church at 2309 Packard Road, a development which was to have unusual and ecumenical ramifications for both groups.
After several years of leasing school facilities at Lawton, and renting St. Clare's for religious services, mid-week Hebrew school, and office space for the Rabbi, the congregation recognized the need for one building which could house all of the Temple's diverse functions. The Board initiated a capital fund-raising campaign. At the Temple Board meeting in June 1974, the Rev. Douglas Evett of St. Clare's came to invite "Temple Beth Emeth to join us in this place". Discussions with members of both congregations took several months and culminated in June 1975 with approval to form a corporation officially named Genesis of Ann Arbor. This arrangement, unique in the country at the time, defined the joint sharing and owning of a single facility by a Jewish and Christian congregation. A gala weekend dedication, preceded by the installation of the Star of David along side the Cross in front of the building on Packard Road was held on May 30-31, 1975. Newspapers throughout the country carried stories about this unique joint venture. The event was sufficiently newsworthy for the NBC evening news team to spend four days filming religious services and educational programs of the two congregations. A small portion of the film was seen on national television in the following week.
In the spring of 1975, Rabbi Warshal accepted an offer to become the spiritual leader of the prestigious Touro Synagogue in New Orleans. A search committee, aided by the UAHC regional director, and the placement director of the Central Conference of Rabbis (CCAR) considered a panel of candidates. That summer, Rabbi Ralph Mecklenburger, who had served as assistant Rabbi in San Francisco, became the second spiritual leader of Temple Beth Emeth.
The Genesis Agreement included a commitment to construct an addition to the church building for religious school classrooms, and to enlarge the existing social hall, with a new kitchen. The Temple launched a building campaign which included bingo games on Sunday evenings as one of its components. Ground was broken for the addition in September, 1977, and appropriately it was the children of both congregations who shoveled the first sod. The new facility was formally dedicated on the weekend of November 11-12, 1978 with a special religious school service on Shabbat morning, and a joint Genesis reception on Saturday evening in the new social hall.
In 1983 when Rabbi Mecklenburger was selected as an assistant Rabbi for Beth El, a large congregation in Fort Worth, Texas, once again the CCAR and UAHC staff aided a search committee in the selection of a new Rabbi. Robert D. Levy, then Assistant Rabbi of Temple Israel in Columbus, Ohio, was chosen as Beth Emeth's third spiritual leader. In the interim between December 1983 and Rabbi Levy's arrival in April 1984, the congregation engaged Rabbi Richard Hertz, then retired from Temple Beth El, Detroit, to conduct services on a part-time basis. Members of the Temple carried out the necessary functions, including leading services in this period. Despite the fact that the Ann Arbor community now offered several alternatives for religious affiliation (Beth Israel Congregation, Orthodox Minyan, Chabad and Jewish Cultural Society), the membership of Temple Beth Emeth continued to grow. Once again, space became an issue. Some members of the temple were concerned with the disparity of size between TBE and St. Clare's, and the differing building use needs.
Long range planning efforts were launched in 1986, and again in 1988. A master plan and program developed by Anderson-Jacobs, an architectural firm was considered but not approved. In 1990, under the leadership of Dannemiller and Tyson, a local consulting group, the Temple launched a long range planning process which they called TBE 2000. The conclusion of this very intensive process was that the congregation supported Genesis, and would make plans to enlarge the facility for both congregations. The architectural firm of Hilberry Associates was hired to design a major building renovation. At their annual "Erev" Thanksgiving service, November 23, 1994, Temple Beth Emeth and St. Clare's officially dedicated the new building which included a new sanctuary, a religious school classroom wing, a new social hall and kitchen, offices and a small Jewish chapel. CNN filmed the service and showed a small clip in their news coverage on Thanksgiving day.
Beginning with the joint Thanksgiving service in 1999, St. Clare's and Temple Beth Emeth launched a year of celebration to commemorate the twenty-fifth anniversary of the Genesis Agreement. Joint activities included a musical performance by the combined choirs of each congregation, the annual dessert Seder, a Genesis publication, and the building of a Habitat for Humanity House in Ann Arbor. The highlight of the year occurred on May 21, 2000. Beginning with a ceremony of commemoration with clergy of both congregations, Rabbi Bruce Warshal, the first Rabbi, and Bishop Wendell Gibbs participating, everyone gathered for a picnic on the front lawn, indicated their continuing commitment to Genesis by signing a plaque, and then enjoyed a concert by the Gemini Brothers in the sanctuary.
This history is an abbreviated version of a document found in the Archives folder of this record group. More detailed information about the temple may be found in the history edited by Linda Vanek and Rose Vainstein entitled Temple Beth Emeth: The First Fifteen Years, 1966-1981 (1982) found in the records of Temple Beth Emeth.
The records of Temple Beth Emeth document the founding and growth of the Ann Arbor reformed congregation. The records include minutes of board and congregational meetings; publications, including history of the temple and service bulletins; subject files relating to community involvement and issues; and photographs.
The record group has been separated into seven series: Administrative; Leadership; Temple Organizations; Topical files: History, Membership, and Miscellaneous; Congregational Life; Genesis and Audio-Visual.
Subjects:
Temple Beth Emeth (Ann Arbor, Mich.); Ann Arbor (Mich.)--Religion.; Genesis Corporation (Ann Arbor, Mich.); Jews--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; St. Clare of Assisi Episcopal Church (Ann Arbor, Mich.); Synagogues--Michigan--Ann Arbor.
Subjects - Visual Materials:
Temple Beth Emeth (Ann Arbor, Mich.); Jews--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Demonstrations--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Pierce, Edward, 1930-; Wheeler, Albert Harold, 1915-1994.
Genre Terms:
Photographs.; Videotapes.
- Administrative
  Administrative consists primarily of Board and Congregational Meeting minutes. There are also Bylaws and Financial information.
  - Temple Bylaws (Box 1)
  - Board minutes May 1966-June 1984, 19 folders (Box 1)
  - Board Minutes July 1984-June 1995, 11 folders (Box 2)
  - Board materials 1988-1992, 1 folders (Box 2)
    (include some duplicate minutes)
  - Meetings
    - Organizational February-April 1966 (Box 2)
    - Congregational meeting minutes April 1966-June 1981, 21 folders (Box 2)
    - Congregational Meeting Minutes June 1982-June 1995, 14 folders (Box 3)
  - Financial
    - Budgets (Box 3)
    - Statements to Congregation (Box 3)
    - Fund Raising Activities (Box 3)
- Leadership
  Sermons and Correspondence of the Temple's three Rabbis and Correspondence of the Temple Presidents comprise the Leadership series.
  - Rabbis
    - Bruce Warshal
      - Installation (Box 3)
      - Other (Box 3)
    - Ralph Mecklenburger
      - Correspondence (Box 3)
      - Sermons (Box 3)
    - Robert Levy
      - Correspondence 1985-1992, 4 folders (Box 3)
      - Sermons 1984-1985, 2 folders (Box 3)
  - Presidents
    - Addresses
      - State of the Temple (Box 3)
    - Correspondence
      includes dates of Presidency; correspondence May span a greater period of time
      - Ron Tikofsky 1965-1969 (Box 3)
      - Allyn Kantor 1969-1971 (Box 3)
      - Paul Vanek 1971-1973 (Box 3)
      - Steve Young 1973-1975, 2 folders (Box 3)
      - Gilbert Small 1975-1977 (Box 3)
      - Marilyn Scott 1977-1980 (Box 3)
      - Irving Fox 1980-1982 (Box 3)
      - Alan Cotzin 1985-1987 (Box 3)
      - Art Lindenberg 1988-1989 (Box 3)
      - Steve Rhodes 1989-1990 (Box 3)
      - Stu Simon 1991-1993 (Box 3)
      - Barbara Heilveil,1993-1994 (Box 3)
- Temple Organizations
  Included in the Temple Organizations series are papers from several Committees, the Religious School, and Temple Social groups.
  - Committees
    - Temple Board Members and Committee Chairs (Box 4)
    - Pulpit, 8 folders (Box 4)
    - Pulpit, 2 folders (Box 4)
    - Religious Affairs, 2 folders (Box 4)
    - Religious Education 1978-1988, 6 folders (Box 4)
    - Fellowship (Box 4)
  - Religious School
    - Administration (Sandra Raben) (Box 4)
    - Curriculum (Box 4)
    - Early Years (Box 4)
    - Calendar (Box 4)
    - School Years 1978-1994 (Box 4)
    - Hebrew School (Box 4)
    - Staff and student rosters 1966-1995 (Box 4)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 4)
  - Social
    - Men's Club (Box 4)
    - Men's Rap Group 1990-1998 (Box 4)
    - Couples Club (Box 5)
    - Singles Club (Box 5)
    - Connections (Box 5)
    - Sisterhood
      - Board Minutes 1967-1988, 5 folders (Box 5)
      - Golden Book: Best wishes, congratulations, in honor of members (Box 5)
- Topical files: History, Membership, and Miscellaneous
  Various representations of Temple history make up the Topical files: History, Membership, and Miscellaneous series.
  - Anniversary Celebrations (Box 5)
  - Anniversary, Temple Bat Mitzvah November 1979 (Box 5)
  - Anniversary, Twenty-fifth Anniversary Year 1991-1992 (Box 5)
  - Archives (Box 5)
  - Chapel dedication May 1998 (Box 5)
  - Cotzins, celebration for May 1996 (Box 5)
  - Dedication of Torah October 1966 (Box 5)
  - Directories 1966-2004, 2 folders (Box 5)
  - Family records (Box 5)
  - History: Temple Beth Emeth: The First Fifteen Years 1966-1981, 2 folders (Box 5)
    (1 folder relates to press coverage of the history)
  - Informational Brochures/Packets (Box 5)
  - Liheyot Committee 1996 (Box 5)
  - Membership: Owner's Manual (Box 5)
  - Mortgage reduction 1998 (Box 5)
  - Newspaper Articles
    - 1966-1982, 17 folders (Box 5)
    - 1983-1985, 1987-1994, 11 folders (Box 6)
  - Planning
    - Program of Development 1973 (Box 6)
    - Long Range Planning Committee 1982 (Box 6)
    - Long Range Task Forces 1986-1987 (Box 6)
    - Needs Assessment 1988 (Box 6)
    - "TBE 2000" 1990, long range planning (Box 6)
    - Long range planning 2000-2001 (Box 6)
    - Long range planning 2001-2002 (Box 6)
  - Program of Development (Box 6)
  - Task Forces: Administrative, Leadership Development, Programming (Box 6)
  - Temple Members (Box 6)
  - Union of American Hebrew Congregations
    - Biennial conferences general (Box 6)
    - Regional biennial conference, Ann Arbor 1992 (Box 6)
    - Membership dues 1968-1972 (Box 6)
    - Publications (Box 6)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 6)
- Congregational Life
  Congregational Life covers Jewish Life, Social and Community Action, and the Temple's publications. There are two cookbooks included, as well as bulletins covering the entire lifespan of the temple.
  - Jewish Life
    - Year of the Jewish Home 5740 (Box 7)
    - Year of Human Awareness 1989-1990 (Box 7)
    - Year of the Spirit 1990-1991 (Box 7)
    - Weekend of Spiritual Renewal 1992 (Box 7)
    - Weekend of Caring June 1993 (Box 7)
    - Jewish Arts Festival (Box 7)
    - Music/Arts Festival December 1987 (Box 7)
  - Services
    - High Holy Days 1988-2000, 3 folders (Box 7)
    - Shabbat and Holiday Observance (Box 7)
    - Temple Service Programs (Box 7)
  - Social and Community Action
    - Black Economic Development League (Box 7)
    - Affirmation of Human Dignity 1982 (Box 7)
    - Jewish Community Rally March 1982 (photographs) (Box 7)
    - Rally for Human Dignity and Freedom March 1982 (photographs) (Box 7)
    - Assisting Refugees (Box 7)
    - Social Action (Box 7)
    - Interfaith Council of Congregations (Box 7)
    - Mitzvah Day 1998-2009, 4 folders (Box 7)
  - Publications
    - Newsletters 1975, 1990-1998 (scattered dates) (Box 7)
    - Cookbooks (Box 7)
    - Temple Bulletins 1966-1993, 22 folders; 4 volumes (Box 8)
- Genesis
  Genesis, the organization created jointly by Temple Beth Emeth and St. Clare Episcopal Church for the ownership of the building, is the final series. It includes the history of the agreement and related celebrations.
  - Record volume: Agreement, by-laws and minutes June 19, 1974-May 22, 1978 (Box 9)
  - Record volume: Minutes June 11, 1978-September 24, 1981 (Box 9)
  - Agreements/By-laws (Box 9)
  - History and Development (Box 9)
  - Celebrations 1975-1978 (Box 9)
  - Building Campaign 1976 (Box 9)
  - Building Addition 1974-1977 (Box 9)
  - Building Committee (Box 9)
  - Tenth Year Celebration (Box 9)
  - Long Range Plan 1988-1989 (Box 9)
  - Building Campaign 1992 (Box 9)
  - Joint Service Programs (Box 9)
  - Background and Informational Materials (Box 9)
  - Genesis House, 25th Anniversary 1999-2000, 2 folders (Box 9)
- Audio-Visual Materials
  The Audio-Visual series consists of VHS tapes and photographs of Temple activities and social occasions.
  - Kol Halev, compact disc (Box 10)
  - Photographs
    - Temple Anniversary Dinner, McKenny Union-EMU, Speaker: Rabbi Ira Youdevin 1981 (Box 10)
    - Temple Annual Meetings, Board Photographs, Past Presidents 1981-1984 (Box 10)
    - Shauvet Celebration 1982 (Box 10)
    - Temple Anniversary Dinner, McKenny Union-EMU, Speaker: Al Vorspan February 1982 (Box 10)
    - Oneg Shabbat, Honoring Debbie Salinger & Jon Falk-marriage November 19, 1982 (Box 10)
    - Temple Anniversary, Campus Inn, Speaker: Rabbi Randall Falk January 1983 (Box 10)
    - Genesis Farewell Party, For Mecklenburgers December 1983 (Box 10)
    - Temple Anniversary Dinner, Farewell to the Mecklenburgers December 1983 (Box 10)
    - Sisterhood Jewish Arts Festival by Traditions December 1984 (Box 10)
    - Temple Dinner, Weber's Inn, Honorees: Bernice & Harold Mark May 1986 (Box 10)
    - Miscellaneous Photographs, Temple Membership Directory 1989 (Box 10)
    - Sam & Eva Taylor Dinner Dance 1989 (Box 10)
    - Genesis Seder April 4, 1991 (Box 10)
    - 25th Anniversary Dinner Dance, Weber's Inn November 16, 1991 (Box 10)
    - Farfel Follies, TBE Talent Show, 25th Anniversary Celebration April 12, 1992 (Box 10)
    - TBE Board Retreat, Home of Stu Simon, Pres. August 1992 (Box 10)
    - Temple Beth Emeth Trip to Farm May 2, 1993 (Box 10)
    - Community Events, Baskin Sculpture, Israel Bond Tribute, UAHC Social Action Award October 22, 1993 (Box 10)
    - Shabbat on a Stab. February 21, 1994 (Box 10)
    - Brotherhood Canoe Trip 1995 (Box 10)
    - Hanukkah Latke Dinner 1995 (Box 10)
    - Sukkot 1995 (Box 10)
    - Debbie Friedman, Concert/Dinner March 18, 1995 (Box 10)
    - Religious School Photographs 1996 (Box 10)
    - Religious School Passover Liberation Experience 1997 (Box 10)
    - Genesis 25th Celebration, Picnic, Spellman's Party May 20-21, 2000 (Box 10)
    - Consultation on Conscious 2005 (Box 10)
  - Videotapes (VHS)
    - Purimspiel 1989 (Box 10)
    - Purimspiel 1990 (Box 10)
      (Levy and Pollack vs. Dobrusin and Greenfield)
    - 25th Anniversary, Farfel Follies April 12, 1992 (Box 10)
    - A Conversation with Carol Plumer, The History of St. Clare's and Genesis of Ann Arbor July 1993 (Box 10)
    - Thanksgiving Celebration and New Sanctuary Dedication November 23, 1994 (Box 10)
    - Service and Program to Celebrate 25 Years of Ministry, The Reverend Douglas P. Evett, Rector February, 1998, 2 videotapes VHS [TM] (Box 10)
    - Ron Wolfson I (Box 10)
    - Ron Wolfson II (Box 10)